Sahaja Yogi: This is the recording of the advice given by Her Holiness Shri Mataji on
Sahaja Yogi: Bu, 19 - 21 Mart 1976 tarihleri arasında Cowasji Jehangir Salonunda
the occasion of three days seminar held at Cowasji Jehangir Hall [Mumbai] from 19 to
[Mumbai] düzenlenen üç günlük bu seminer vesilesiyle, Kutsal Shri Mataji tarafından
21st March 1976.
verilen tavsiyelerin kaydıdır.
This is a recording of the first day that is of the 19th March 1976.
Bu 19 Mart 1976 tarihinde yapılan seminerin ilk günündeki kayıttır.
Shri Mataji: After a very long time, we are again assembled in this hall.
Shri Mataji: Çok uzun bir aradan sonra yeniden bu salonda toplandık.
When Sahaja Yoga was just in its infancy, we had arranged a program in this hall.
Sahaja Yoga henüz başlangıç aşamasındayken, bu salonda bir program düzenlemiştik.
Since then, by God’s grace, Sahaja Yoga has settled, in the minds of the Sahaja Yogis.
O zamandan beri, Tanrı’nın lütfuyla Sahaja Yoga, Sahaja Yogilerin zihinlerine yerleşti.
As if the rain has been absorbed by the hungry Earth.
Sanki yağmur aç toprak tarafından emilmiş gibi.
Sahaja Yoga is not meant for people who are superficial and are not seeking within themselves
Sahaja Yoga, yüzeysel olan ve kendi içlerinde, tüm arayış içinde
and with all the earnestness and the hankering of all seekers.
olanların olanca ciddiyeti ve arzusu içinde aramayan insanlar için değildir.
It is not meant for people who are seeking God in the books.
Bu, Tanrıyı kitaplarda arayan insanlara yönelik değildir.
Because God is not there.
Çünkü Tanrı orada değildir.
It is also not meant for people who think they can achieve God.
Bu Tanrı'ya ulaşabileceklerini düşünen insanlar için de geçerli değildir.
That they can by their efforts, by their extreme ‘hatha‘ as we call it, ‘obstinacy’,
Onlar kendi çabalarıyla, bizim 'inatçılık' dediğimiz bu aşırı 'hatha'larıyla
win the grace of God.
(zorla, güç kullanarak), Tanrı'nın lütfunu kazanabilirler.
It is meant for those people who are, from the heart, all the time asking for Him.
Bu, her zaman O'nu yürekten isteyen insanlar içindir.
And looking for Him, for the genuine and for the reality.
Ve O'nu aramak, hakikat içindir ve gerçek içindir.
‘Sahaja’ – I have told you many a time, ‘saha’ means ‘within’ and ‘ja’
'Sahaja' – bunu size defalarca anlattım, 'Saha' kelimesi 'içinizde' anlamına gelir
means ‘born with you’.
ve 'ja' ise 'seninle doğan' anlamına gelir.
I have elaborately told you many a time what is ‘sahaja‘.
Size defalarca ‘sahaja’nın ne olduğunu detaylı bir şekilde anlattım.
It is a ‘spontaneous’ growth of your being into that infinite realm of God’s grace.
Bu, varlığınızın Tanrı'nın lütfunun sonsuz alanına doğru 'kendiliğinden' büyümesidir.
We have to enter into the Kingdom of God.
Bizler Tanrı'nın Krallığına girmeliyiz.
Not by words, not by deeds, but it has to be the actualisation of the experience.
Sözle değil, eylemle değil, bu deneyimin gerçekleşmesi olmalıdır.
If you are satisfied by the tomfoolery and the spiritual jugglery that is going on, it
Eğer siz bu süregelen kurnazlıklardan ve ruhsal hokkabazlıklardan memnunsanız,
is better that you take to that course and be lost.
o yolu izlemeniz ve orada kaybolmanız daha iyidir.
But for Sahaja, you have to be an earnest and genuine seeker.
Fakat Sahaja için, siz ciddi ve gerçek bir arayan olmalısınız.
Whatever mistakes you have committed in your search will be forgiven by God, because He
Aramanız sırasında yaptığınız hatalar, her ne olursa olsun, bunlar Tanrı tarafından affedilecektir
knows that it was in ignorance that all these mistakes were committed.
çünkü O, tüm bu hataların cehalet nedeniyle yapıldığını biliyor.
We have here some Sahaja Yogis who know this.
Burada bunu bilen bazı Sahaja Yogilerimiz var
But when I see people, and I have experience of them, I am sometimes surprised the way
ama insanları gördüğümde ve onlarla ilgili deneyim kazandığımda,
they are contradictory to themselves.
bazen onların kendileriyle çelişmelerine şaşırıyorum.
How they live with those contradictory ideas; it is something beyond the imagination of
Bu çelişkili düşüncelerle nasıl yaşıyorlar.
God Almighty also.
Bu, Yüce Tanrı'nın da tasavvurunun ötesinde bir şeydir.
It has been since ages, one simple question, “How to reach the Infinite, through this
Çağlar boyunca süregelen basit bir soru var: "Tanrı'nın bize verdiği bu akıl sayesinde,
finite mind, through this rationality which God has given us."
bu sonlu zihin vasıtasıyla, Sonsuz olana nasıl ulaşılır."
This is the eternal problem which has been there from the times of Socrates, Confucius,
Bu, Sokrates, Konfüçyüs, Hegel, Kant’ın zamanından beri
Kant, Hegel.
var olan ezeli bir sorundur.
All these great philosophers have been only asking this question in all their findings
Tüm bu büyük filozoflar, tüm bulgularında ve araştırmalarında sadece şu soruyu soruyorlar:
and searches, “How to reach the Infinite through this finite?”
"Bu sonlu olandan, Sonsuz olana nasıl ulaşılır?"
As it is, the human being is made that way, that he has to worry for himself and also
Zaten insan öyle yaratılmıştır ki hem kendisi için endişe eder
worry about God’s knowing.
hem de Tanrıyı bilmek için tasalanır,
He is also worried about how God is going to give him this blessing.
Tanrı'nın kendisine bu kutsamayı nasıl vereceği hususunda da kaygı duyar,
Who has created you?
sizi kim yarattı,
Who has created this Universe?
bu evreni kim yarattı?
Who has created this beautiful heaven for you here?
Buradaki bu güzel cenneti sizin için kim yarattı?
But you are worried how He is going to give you that blessing by which you will know the
ama siz kendi içinizdeki cenneti tanıyacağınız bu kutsamayı,
heaven within yourself.
O'nun size nasıl vereceği hususunda endişe ediyorsunuz.
You are worried how He is going to bestow upon you the bliss of self-knowledge.
O'nun size kendi özünüzün bilgisini nasıl bahşedeceği için endişe ediyorsunuz.
You need not worry.
Endişelenmenize gerek yok,
It is His job.
bu O’nun işidir
But He has made you like this.
ama sizi bu hale getiren O'dur.
He has made you this way, especially, with a purpose.
O sizi özellikle belli amaç için bu şekilde yarattı.
The articulation of your personality came into being.
Kişiliğinizin bağdaşması ortaya çıktı.
Just like any egg develops a shell around itself to grow, in the same way, you also
Tıpkı herhangi bir yumurtanın büyümek için kendi etrafında bir kabuk geliştirmesi gibi,
develop a shell in which you have to develop your personality, your being in such a manner
aynı şekilde siz de kendi kişiliğinizi, varlığınızı belli bir şekilde geliştirmek için
that ultimately you become the proper instrument to receive that knowledge that is God, that
size gereken bir kabuk geliştirirsiniz ve en sonunda siz, Tanrı olan, İlahi olan
is Divine.
bu bilgiyi almaya
And then to emit it to others.
uygun bir enstrüman haline gelirsiniz
And to see it.
ve sonrasında, bunu başkalarına yaymak için
To be aware of it.
ve Onu görmek için, bunun farkında olmak için,
To be a Sakshi.
Sakshi olmak için, içinizden akan
To be a witness.
Tanrısallığa şahit olmak için.
Of that Divine flowing through you.
Elbette ki bu filozoflardan bazılarının,
Of course, some of these philosophers never had any inkling of that Divine.
bu Tanrısallık hakkında hiçbir fikri yoktu.
Some of them did have; that is why there is such a disparity to what they say.
Bazılarının ise vardı; işte bu yüzden onların söyledikleri arasında bu kadar fark var
But then have been really genuine people, most of them.
ama çoğu gerçekten samimi insanlardı
And they have been honest about not finding it or finding it.
ve onu bulmak ya da bulmamak konusunda dürüst davrandılar.
But today, it is the worst time of hypocrisy, known as Kali Yuga, in which every Dick, Tom,
Ama bugün, Kali Yuga olarak bilinen bu zaman, ikiyüzlülüğün en kötü zamanıdır; buradaki her bir
Harry has started claiming that he is the person who is going to introduce you to Him.
Dick, Tom, Harry, sizi Onunla tanıştıracak olan kişinin kendisi olduğunu iddia etmeye başlamıştır
And he has formed his own ideas and his own imagination to give you that, this is how
ve o kişi size bunu vermek için kendi fikirlerini ve kendi hayal gücünü oluşturdu,
you are going to receive Him, “I have got it, all right."
siz O'nu bu şekilde kabul edeceksiniz, "Anladım, tamam."
There is one good thing about Kali Yuga I think – that all the ancient scriptures
Kali Yuga'nın bence tek bir iyi yanı var;
are for you written down a long time back.
eski kutsal yazılar sizler için çok uzun zaman önce yazılmıştır
And you have to tally.
ve sizin çetelesini tutmanız gerekir,
If it is the Bible, it is there.
eğer bu İncil de ise, oradadır.
If it is Koran, it is there.
Eğer bu Kuran da varsa bu oradadır.
And if it is anyone of the Vedas, it is there.
Ve eğer bu Vedalardan birisindeyse, o oradadır.
But when you start your new scriptures and new ideologies and try to fit in everything
Ama siz yeni yazıtlarınızı ve yeni ideolojilerinizi başlattığınızda ve siz her şeyi
according to that, when you try to mould God into your own sorts of weaknesses, then how
buna uydurmaya çalıştığınızda, Tanrı'yı kendi zayıflıklarınıza göre şekillendirmeye çalıştığınızda,
can you be sahaj, spontaneous?
o zaman siz sahaj, kendiliğinden / spontan olabilir misiniz?
So, the problem today is Kali Yuga.
Yani bugünün sorunu Kali Yuga'dır.
Is much worse than it was ever before.
Bu daha önce olduğundan çok daha kötüdür.
Because apart from the original articulation we have had, we have many more articulations
Çünkü sahip olduğumuz orijinal bağdaştırmanızın dışında, üzerimizde daha birçok
on us.
bağdaştırmanız daha var.
The worst of all is the mental articulation, that we think by reading books, by talking
Hepsinden kötüsü, kitap okuyarak, onun hakkında konuşarak, konferans vererek
about it, by giving lectures and receiving lectures, you are going to achieve it.
ve konferans dinleyerek bunu başaracağınızı düşündüğümüz zihinsel bir ifadedir.
You are sadly mistaken.
Ne yazık ki üzücü şekilde yanılıyorsunuz.
This is the greatest maya or illusion, I think, of the present.
Bana göre bu, günümüzün en büyük Mayası ya da yanılsamasıdır.
Other mayas can be conquered, but this is one of the most elusive temptations for the
Diğer maya’ların da üstesinden gelinebilir, ancak modern insan için, okuyarak, Tanrı hakkında bir şeyler
modern man, that he thinks by reading, by listening about God, he is going to achieve.
dinleyerek bunu başaracağını düşünmesi, hakkından gelinmesi en zor yoldan çıkarımlardan birisidir.
It is spontaneous.
Bu kendiliğindendir.
Let us understand what is spontaneous.
Neyin spontan olduğunu anlayalım.
Spontaneous is a natural, living thing that happens to us.
Kendiliğindenlik başımıza gelen şey doğal, canlı bir şeydir.
For example, if you see a seed – if you plant it, it spontaneously grows.
Mesela eğer siz bir tohum görür ve onu ekerseniz, o kendiliğinden büyür.
Do you stand on your head in front of that seed?
O tohumun karşısına geçip, tepe üstü mü duruyorsunuz?
Or do you read books?
Yoksa kitap mı okuyorsunuz?
Or does the seed have to read books of germination, to get germinated?
Veya o tohumun çimlenmek için, kalkıp çimlenme kitaplarını mı okuması gerekiyor?
Not that.
Böyle değil.
Never!
Asla!
But it is only a human being who thinks foolishly, which an ordinary dog also does not do that.
Ama sıradan bir köpek bile bunu yapmaz, sadece aptalca düşünen bir insan bunu yapar.
You may say that; there are books which are Truth, there are books which are pouring reality.
Şunu söyleyebilirsiniz; Gerçek olan kitaplar var, gerçekliği ortaya döken kitaplar var
But have you got the measure to know which are the books which are pouring reality, and
ama hangi kitapların gerçeği ortaya döktüğünü, hangilerinin ise böyle olmadığını bilecek
which are not?
bir ölçüte sahip misiniz?
There are gurus, who are of course prospering materially better because they tell you to
Maddi olarak iyi bir şekilde zenginleşen gurular var çünkü onlar size sanyasa (Her şeyi bırakmak)
take sanyasa, “You take sanyasa, you renounce and bring all the money to me”.
almanızı söylüyorlar, "Sanyasa alın, her şeyden vazgeçin ve tüm parayı siz bana getirin".
And foolishly so many human beings are attached and attracted towards such people.
Ve aptalca bir şekilde pek çok insan bu tür insanlara bağlanıyor ve onlara ilgi duyuyor.
Why?
Neden?
Because our articulation has given way to this darkness that we go to something false
Çünkü bağdaştırmamız yerini bu karanlığa bırakmış, gerçeklikten çok daha
much faster than to reality.
hızlı bir şekilde, bizler sahte bir şeye doğru gidiyoruz.
We are shaken up within ourselves.
Kendi içimizde sarsılıyoruz.
We do not have the strength to hold onto the reality, to ask for the reality.
Gerçeğe tutunacak, gerçeği isteyecek gücümüz yok.
They have to give us reality!
Onların bize gerçeği vermeleri gerekiyor!
So, anybody who speaks, you see, in a bombastic manner, quotations over quotations, reading
Yani, gördüğünüz gibi abartılı bir şekilde konuşan herkes, alıntı üzerine alıntı yapıyor,
this, reading that, giving big lectures; people are very much fascinated.
şunu okuyor, bunu okuyor, büyük konferanslar veriyor; insanlar çok hayran oluyor.
They think by listening to lectures, you are going to have it.
Onlar konuşmaları dinleyerek bunu başaracağınızı düşünüyorlar.
Never, never.
Asla asla.
It is going to happen to you.
Bu sizin başına gelecek.
You have been to so many lectures before.
Daha önce pek çok konuşma dinlediniz.
You have listened to so many people.
O kadar çok insanı dinlediniz ki.
There have been many gurus – good and bad.
İyi ve kötü pek çok guru vardı.
Have you been able to make out who is a real guru and who is not?
Kimin gerçek guru olup, kimin olmadığını anlayabildiniz mi?
How will you know that this man is talking from the seventh heaven?
Bu adamın cennetin yedinci katından konuştuğunu siz nasıl bileceksiniz?
It may be a rakshasa, talking to you.
Sizinle konuşan kişi, bir rakshasa olabilir.
It may be a devil incarnated in these horrible days.
Bu korkunç günlerde enkarne olmuş bir şeytan olabilir.
He could be anything who is talking to you.
Sizinle konuşan kişi, herhangi biri olabilir.
What makes you believe that some person who is behaving like a godman is a real godman
Bir Tanrı-insan gibi davranan birisinin gerçek bir Tanrı-insan olup olmadığına,
or not?
sizi inandıran şey nedir?
There is a way.
Bir yolu var.
And that is why, when is more necessary, the things happen by which you know.
İşte bu yüzden, daha gerekli olduğunda, bildiğiniz bir şeyler olur.
You have to become something else to know what is wrong.
Neyin yanlış olduğunu anlamak için sizin başka bir şey olmanız gerekir.
You have to be reborn.
Sizler yeniden doğmalısınız.
You have to be baptized.
Vaftiz edilmeniz gerekiyor.
You have to become a Brahmin.
Brahman olmalısınız.
You have to become a Mussalman.
Müslüman olmalısınız.
You have to become a Christian.
Hıristiyan olmanız gerekiyor.
You are to be reborn.
Yeniden doğacaksınız.
You are born with a body; you are born with a mind which is articulated.
Bir bedenle doğdunuz; bağdaşmış bir zihinle doğdunuz.
You have to jump into that Infinite Love of God to know Who is emitting that Love.
Bu Sevgiyi Kimin yaydığını bilmek için Tanrı'nın Sonsuz Sevgisi içine atlamalısınız.
And then the knowledge comes to you.
Ve o zaman bilgi size gelir.
Unless and until your eyes are opened, don’t believe into any personality because he knows
Gözleriniz açılmadıkça hiçbir şahsa inanmayın çünkü o sizi nasıl etkileyeceğini
how to impress you people, and even not Me, unless and until I give you everything, I
biliyor, Ben size her şeyi vermediğim sürece hatta Bana bile inanmayın
give you that which you are seeking.
ve Ben size aradığınızı veririm.
You must ask for the Reality.
Gerçeği istemek zorundasınız.
Ask for that from Me.
Bunu Benden isteyin.
I cannot give you anything else but that.
Ben size bundan başka bir şey veremem.
Unless and until you have had that experience, the actualisation of that, of the Sahaja Yoga
Kendi içinizde kutsamaları aldığınız ve bunu hissettiğiniz Sahaja Yoga'nın bu deneyimini,
by which you receive the blessings within yourselves and you feel it and it emits through
bunun gerçekleşmesini yaşamadığınız sürece inanmayın ve bu, kollarınız ve bacaklarınız
your extremities.
vasıtasıyla yayılır.
And you see that power flowing through you which is known as the Chaitanya Lahari [Waves
Ve bu günlerde kimsenin okumadığı Adi Shankaracharya tarafından çok iyi bir şekilde
of Bliss] which was very well described by Adi Shankaracharya, whom nobody reads these
tarif edilen, Chaitanya Lahari [Kutsal Ruhun Serin Esintisi] olarak bilinen bu gücün
days.
içinizden aktığını görürsünüz.
They want to read somebody who talks of sex.
Onlar seksten bahseden birisini okumak istiyorlar.
The mind is so much attached to sex, that everything must come through sex; otherwise,
Zihin sekse o kadar bağlıdır ki her şey seks yoluyla gerçekleşmelidir;
nothing goes here.
aksi takdirde burada hiçbir şey olmaz.
These people who try to impress you try to work on your weakness.
Sizi etkilemeye çalışan bu insanlar zayıf noktanız üzerinde çalışmaya çalışırlar
But a Mother is not going to do that.
ama bir Anne bunu yapmaz.
A Mother is going to give you the real that is there and is going to tell you that, “My
Bir Anne sana orada olan gerçeği verecek ve sana şunu söyleyecektir:
child, this has been wrong and you have to get detached from that idea.
“Çocuğum, bu yanlıştı ve senin bu fikirden kopman gerekiyor.
And stand within yourselves."
Ve kendi içinizde dik durun.
Every one of them, those who have been great, has been saying, “Na yoga, na sankya”
Büyük olanların her biri şunu söylüyor: "Na yoga, na sankya"
[neither yoga nor reasoning] – Shankaracharya’s.
(ne yoga ne de akıl yürütme) - Shankaracharya'nınki ama Shankaracharya
But Hindus are the first who will go to yoga – to hatha yoga.
bu yogalardan hiç birini tatbik etmediği halde yogaya,
When Shankaracharya never did anyone of these yoga’s.
hatha yoga'ya ilk gidecek olanlar, Hindulardır.
Yoga’s are meant for very, very few people.
Yoga çok çok az sayıda insan içindir.
For very few people who live with a guru, in the jungles.
Ormanlarda bir guru ile yaşayan çok az insan içindir.
You have to do six things simultaneously under the guidance of an evolved soul.
Evrimleşmiş bir ruhun rehberliği altında altı şeyi aynı anda yapmalısınız
But everybody is trying to do yoga because they want to slim down.
ama herkes zayıflamak istediği için yoga yapmaya çalışıyor.
God is not to be used for these frivolous things.
Tanrı bu anlamsız şeyler için kullanılmamalıdır.
All right, you do exercises.
Tamam, siz egzersiz yapın
But this is not yoga.
ama bu yoga değildir.
Yoga means ‘union with God’.
Yoga kelimesi, 'Tanrı ile bir olma' anlamına gelir.
It is union with God.
Bu Tanrı ile bir olmaktır.
It is not union with the worldly things that you think so important.
Bu kadar önemli olduğunu düşündüğünüz şey, dünyevi şeylerle birleşmek değildir.
Those who go to the extremes of things are also no good for Sahaja Yoga.
Aşırı uçlara gidenler de, Sahaja Yoga için iyi değildirler.
Extreme takes you away from reality which was said by Gautama Buddha.
Aşırılık sizi Gautama Buddha'nın söylediği gerçeklikten uzaklaştırır.
He said, “Take to the middle path, keep to the middle path."
O, size "orta yola gidin, orta yoldan ilerleyin" dedi
But His disciples have gone to the extreme path.
ama Onun müritleri en uç yola gittiler.
Of foolishness.
Budalalıktan.
He said, “Do not worship any Gods or Goddesses at that time”, because He was in sahaja.
O, o zamanlar "hiçbir Tanrıya veya Tanrıçaya ibadet etmeyin" , dedi. Çünkü O sahaja’daydı.
So, His disciples started worshipping his tooth, nail, everything.
Bunun üzerine müritleri Onun dişine, tırnağına, onun her şeyine tapınmaya başladılar.
Of course, that too has a meaning.
Elbette ki bunun da bir anlamı var
But not for people who are not realised.
ama bu aydınlanma almayan insanlar için değildir.
How can you make out that the hair of Mohammad Saheb is in that place in Kashmir or it is
Muhammed Saheb'in saçının Keşmir'deki o yerde olduğunu nasıl ortaya çıkarabilirsiniz,
of some imposter?
yoksa o saç bir sahtekarın mı?
Have you got any method by which you can detect?
Bunu tespit edebilecek bir yönteminiz var mı?
I can say that it is the hair of Mohammad Saheb.
Bunun Muhammed Saheb'in saçı olduğunu Ben söyleyebilirim.
I say that.
Ben böyle söylüyorum
But why should you accept me also?
ama siz Beni de neden kabul edesiniz ki?
With all your brains and intelligence, why should you accept anything which is not actually
Tüm bu aklınız ve zekanızla, neden aslında farkındalığınıza odaklanmamış,
focused within your awareness?
aslında farkındalığınıza getirilmemiş
Which is not actually brought within your awareness.
herhangi bir şeyi kabul etmeli misiniz?
There is a method.
Bir yöntem var,
There is a way.
bir yol var,
There is an education.
bir eğitim var
But it is a spontaneous one.
ama bu kendiliğinden gelişen bir şey,
It happens to you.
bu sizin başınıza geliyor.
You just become.
Siz sadece olursunuz.
This education comes to you in such a manner, in such a way, that even a child knows.
Bu eğitim size öyle bir şekilde, öyle bir şekilde geliyor ki, bir çocuk bile bunu bilir,
It is a subjective knowledge that comes to you.
bu size gelen subjektif bir bilgidir.
When you jump into that Divine Love through Sahaja Yoga, then you become one with the
Sahaja Yoga aracılığıyla o Tanrısal Sevginin içine atladığınızda,
collective consciousness.
kolektif bilinçle bir olursunuz.
It is not that I tell you that you are collectively conscious, but you become conscious.
Ben size kolektif  bilinçte olduğunuzu söylemiyorum ama siz bilinçli bir hale geliyorsunuz.
For example, now, for Me, when I say that this sari has got a border, you will say,
Mesela şimdi Ben, bu sarinin sınırları var dediğimde,
“Yes of course we know."
siz “Evet elbette biliyoruz” diyeceksiniz.